Downloaded @ subs4free.club
[WAVES CRASHING GENTLY]
[SEAGULLS CALLING]
[SERENE MUSIC FADING IN]
[SERENE MUSIC CONTINUES]
WOMAN: In Orkney, it's said
that people who have drowned
turn into seals.
We call them selkies.
At the highest tides,
they slip off their seal skins
for the night
and they come to the shore
as beautiful people.
And they dance together.
Naked in the moonlight.
[SERENE MUSIC CONTINUES]
The selkies
return to the sea at dawn.
Unless they're seen by a person.
And then they're trapped
in their human body
and cannot return.
And they'll always remain
discontent on land
because they belong to the sea.
[DOOR CREAKS]
Oh, everyone's gone?
BARMAN: Yeah, everyone's gone.
WOMAN: More for me.
BARMAN: Rona?
What are you doing?
[GLASSES AND UTENSILS CLANKING]
Please, please, please, come on.
Come on, I gotta get you out.
- Time to go home.
- Why?
I remember...
BARMAN: That everyone
is really long gone.
No, there was, erm...
[SNICKERS DRUNKENLY]
BARMAN: The lights are on.
RONA: The lights.
BARMAN: That really means
the night is truly...
Ow...
Come on,
what are you doing, Rona?
We gotta get you out now,
come on.
- Come on. Come on, Rona.
- Let's dance.
Fine, I'll dance
with you instead.
- Mm...
- Dave?
[CHUCKLES]
[THUD]
Ah-ha!
- DAVE: Come on.
- Dave.
- Give me a twirl.
- BARMAN: She's long gone.
Come on, love. The door's there
and you're going out of it.
Under the table. Out you come.
Come on. Out you come.
- You're leaving now.
- You can't see me.
- Right, right, right, Dave.
- Come on. Up you go.
Stand up. Stand up.
- [SCATTING]
- To the door.
You're nearly there. Come on.
You've had a bit too much.
BARMAN: Dave,
please just get her out.
- God, I'm strong.
- DAVE: Come on.
- Come on.
- Dave, what are you gonna do?
You gonna make me leave?
- I'm gonna take you outside.
- BARMAN: Rona!
You're gonna
- fucking make me leave?
- Enough!
Fucking arsehole! Ahh!
- DAVE: Time to go.
- Get off of me!
Ow!
- Make him stop!
- Time to go.
RONA: Arsehole!
[PANTING]
[ENGINE REVS]
MAN: Hey, you need a ride?
I can give you a lift,
if you like.
[MOUSE CLICKING]
DOCTOR: Rona.
Um, is it okay if I get
some details from you?
- Mm-hmm.
- Yeah?
Just check your age.
Twenty-nine.
And...
What's your occupation?
Er, I'm unemployed right now.
But I got a masters in biology.
Just get a few more details.
So, are there any illnesses
that run in the family?
Anything, like any heart attacks
or strokes?
No.
Any diabetes?
Anyone in the family
have any kind of mental illness?
[ELECTRONIC DANCE MUSIC PLAYING]
[BEAT DROPS]
- [SHEEP BLEATING]
- [MUSIC CONTINUES]
- [MUSIC STOPS]
- [INSECTS CHIRPING]
[SHEEP BLEATING]
[SNIFFLING]
RONA: Come on.
- I'll just leave it here.
- Thanks.
[SHEEP BLEATING]
[TOOL CLICKS]
WOMAN: How's Dad?
He's fine.
I heard he's been putting
his rants on Facebook again?
He's not.
Have you decided what color
you're gonna
paint the walls yet?
What do you think?
I found...
There's a sort of a... duck egg?
- Not sure.
- That's nice.
Yeah.
That'd be nice
in the living room, I think.
- Matches your trousers.
- [CHUCKLES]
Oh.
Look what I found.
The RSPB is hiring.
For summer jobs.
They're looking for--
I have a life
that I have to get back to.
I know, of course.
And I'll pray for you.
Mum. Don't do that.
[SCOFFS] Of course I do.
Rona, do you want some tea?
I'll be down in a bit.
Okay.
[KETTLE WHISTLING]
[SING-SONGING] I'm really bored.
[MAN CHUCKLES]
Are you bored too?
I see what you're trying to do,
you know.
- [MUFFLED DANCE MUSIC PLAYING]
- [CHILDREN LAUGHING]
Come on, this is almost done.
Trust me, if you can't handle
your book on mushrooms
or whatever that is...
[BOTH LAUGH]
Was it mushrooms?
RONA: Fungi.
No, I hate the way
you barely need to read a book.
And all the facts still
somehow get into your head.
That's 'cause you've been
staring at it for hours.
Yeah, I've been literally
staring at this page--
I know, just leave it
and let's go to the pub!
What was it like
growing up here?
MAN: Growing up in London?
RONA: Yeah.
MAN: Growing up in London
is just...
there is always
low key something.
I didn't actually
really clock it
until the first time
I went to the countryside.
And everything there
was, like, so quiet.
- [SEAGULLS CALLING IN DISTANCE]
- [INDISTINCT CHATTER]
RONA: I'm just going
to get another one,
- is that all right?
- No problem.
[LIGHTER CLICKING]
- Er, excuse me.
- Yeah, sorry?
You don't have a lighter,
do you?
I don't. Sorry.
I'm not a smoker myself.
Right. That's very sensible.
I like your hat you've got on,
by the way.
- Well, thank you.
- Very interesting.
Do I recognize you?
- Possibly, are you from here?
- Yeah, yeah.
Oh, I was thinking
from your accent
you must be from somewhere else.
No, er, my mum and dad
are English.
- So I got a weird accent.
- That'll be it, that'll be it.
Yeah, I've actually...
I've been away
- for about ten years now. So...
- My God, long time.
Yeah, I don't really come back
that often.
So what are you doing now, then?
I'm just going off to meet
a couple of friends.
Ah, friends.
- Yeah.
- [BOTH CHUCKLE]
Yeah, I don't really know
anyone here anymore, so...
I was a bit desperate to...
see if there's anyone younger
hanging around.
MAN: Oh, yes.
Do you wanna have a cup of tea
before you go, maybe?
No, I really can't.
I've got to catch up.
- Another time, maybe.
- Right.
Yeah. I'm staying
with my mum at the minute.
But I usually live
down in London.
I just came to help my dad
with the lambing, so...
But I'm going
back down there soon, so...
Mm. Er, could you
just give me your hand,
so I can try this again?
- Oh, yeah, no problem.
- All right, thanks.
[LIGHTER CLICKING]
- The wind.
- [CHUCKLES] Yeah, it's not easy.
- Got it!
- Yeah, all right.
Okay, I gotta go on.
See you later.
RONA: All right.
[SNIFFS]
[LIGHTER CLICKS]
[INSECTS CHIRPING]
[MUSIC SOUNDING OUT FAINTLY
OVER HEADPHONES]
[SHEEP BLEATING]
[RONA GRUNTS]
[THUD]
[LIGHT ELECTRONIC MUSIC PLAYING]
[FAINT DISTORTED RUMBLING]
RONA: Sometimes you can feel
a vibration in Orkney.
A low rumble.
A tremor.
It takes over the whole island
and every part of your body.
But, of course...
it could all just be
in your head.
Some people say it's the sound
of underwater
military experiments.
[EXPLOSION]
Others say it's the waves
caught in caves
deep below the land.
But the one that brought me
nightmares when I was little
is the oldest theory.
A ginormous monster
called the Mester Muckle
Stoorworm,
who was so big
his tail would wrap around
the whole world.
And he was defeated
by a young lad
called Assipattle.
He killed the Stoorworm
with a burning peat.
Fire burned inside its body.
And it was in such pain
that its neck reached
nine times to the moon and back.
And then its teeth fell out
and formed the Orkney islands.
The liver
is still burning today.
And we feel that as the tremors.
[RUMBLING]
WOMAN 1:
Oh, that was just lovely.
WOMAN 2: Absolutely gorgeous.
More mince,
if anyone wants another.
- Couldn't have any more.
- No, thanks.
WOMAN 2: Rona,
I notice you haven't eaten much.
- You all right?
- Yeah, yeah.
I'm just not hungry,
but it was lovely. Yeah.
WOMAN 3: [SNEEZES] Excuse me.
WOMAN 4: Bless you.
I'd just like to say thank you.
Thank you, Father,
for this delicious food
and for this wonderful company
at my table today.
WOMAN 2: Of course we thank you,
Lord, for the food on our table,
for the sun in the sky...
[INDISTINCT CHATTER]
[GROUP LAUGHING]
WOMAN 5: So are you up for long?
RONA: No, I'm going back down
to London next week.
Just because, um,
there's a service for healing
on a Thursday evening.
You might find it interesting.
Your husband used to go, right?
Yeah, my Mark went,
like, last year.
He was having
a bit of trouble with drinking
and just needed
a bit of guidance
and, you know,
just a bit of support and that.
A bit of help, really,
you know, so...
No, I'm doing fine, so...
WOMAN 5: I mean, anyone can go.
It's not really like...
Rona, your mum was saying
that you're taking a break
from your study?
[BREATHING HEAVILY]
[CAN POPS OPEN]
Rona. Please don't.
Don't what? Don't what? This?
I'm sober. Do they know that?
Because they seem to know
everything else, don't they?
You've clearly told them
everything that's going on.
Rona, I'm sorry.
Come back inside?
Give me a minute.
Mm. Don't start reading
the Bible without me.
[STOMPS]
[SINGING]
We want to see, we want to see
We want to see Jesus lifted high
We want to see...
[BIRDS CHIRPING]
RONA: Get a shift on, Daynin.
Come on.
[LAUGHTER]
Oh, fuck! Oh, fuck!
[INDISTINCT CHATTER]
- WOMAN: Daynin. Rona.
- Daynin.
RONA: Give me your hand!
Ah, give me your hand!
Please, don't.
Two hands on the bicycle!
[SINGING] Happy birthday to you!
[MUFFLED CLUB MUSIC PLAYING]
- Happy birthday...
- [WOMAN COUGHING]
Sorry!
[SINGING] Dear Gloria
Happy birthday...
- [INTENSE CLUB MUSIC CONTINUES]
- [YELLING]
[MUSIC SOFTENS]
[MUSIC FADING OUT]
[SERENE MUSIC FADING IN]
DAYNIN: Hi.
Hi.
[BIRD CHIRPING]
[HUMMING CHEERFULLY]
RONA: Sometimes
when I hallucinate,
I transpose
the island's boundaries
onto a map of London.
In Hackney, thousands of people
live in the same area
of the farm that was home
to just our family.
150 acres.
[SEAGULLS SQUAWKING]
Screaming gulls are sirens,
the sea, traffic.
Tower blocks are cliff faces.
The warning lights
on top of tall buildings
are lighthouses.
The Tower of London
is Skara Brae.
And the Millennium Dome
is the ancient Ring of Brodgar.
[SEAGULLS SQUAWKING]
[SQUAWKING FADES OUT]
- [SIREN WAILING IN DISTANCE]
- [CAR ENGINE RUMBLING]
[INDISTINCT CHATTER]
[YAWNS]
MAN: Rona, I just wanted
a quick catch up really,
- just to see how you are.
- RONA: Yeah, good. Why?
No, it's just that we had
the lab meeting last week
and you weren't there.
Everyone else was there.
Well, yeah, I had, erm,
a dentist appointment that day.
But also, I've just been
really busy with the project.
You could've told me
about the dentist.
I mean, some of the other guys
in the lab,
they said that you sort of
distanced yourself a little bit.
- I did. Erm...
- [PHONE VIBRATES]
That you're not going
to coffee with them
- as much as you used to.
- Sorry. Erm...
[BOTH LAUGHING]
I mean, you had promised
to get a report to me
- last week as well.
- [PHONE VIBRATES]
[DAYNIN SCREAMS]
[SPLASH]
[LAUGHING]
[SERENE MUSIC PLAYING]
[RONA CHUCKLES SOFTLY]
[THUNDER CRASHING]
[THUNDER RUMBLING]
Have you ever felt like
you could control the weather?
Really?
Nah, that's not me.
- RONA: God, you're weird.
- [CHUCKLES]
[RAIN PATTERING]
You all right?
Mm-hmm.
Sure?
RONA: I used to think
my dad could control the wind,
when I was little.
- [DOG BARKING]
- [SHEEP BLEATING]
Dad!
- Dad?
- Yeah.
RONA: There you are.
Hiya.
- Hi.
- You all right?
Yeah.
I'm heading off soon,
so I wanted to say goodbye.
- Are you?
- Yeah.
- Already?
- Mm.
Well, you want to see
a lump of something,
- might be worth a fortune?
- What?
"One test for ambergris
is to poke it
with a hot needle
and a liquid should ooze out."
RONA'S DAD: Here we go.
[RONA GASPS]
Look, look, look, look.
That's liquid. Oh, my God!
Wow.
"Ambergris is a rare
and highly valuable substance
produced in the stomach
of sperm whales,
either vomited or excreted
and found floating on the seas.
It has a bad smell."
Does it have a bad smell?
Doesn't smell like anything.
Still, that is liquid.
- It says for one gram...
- Yes.
...you can get $28.
- What's that, 25 quid? 23 quid?
- Like 25 quid.
Twenty-three, so that's,
that's... this is...
This is ten pounds.
That's four and a half kilos,
that's 4,500, that's... 25...
[WHISPERING]
That's over 100,000 pounds.
[GASPS]
- That's over 100...
- [LAUGHS]
Well done!
[NORMAL TONE]
That is one big tractor.
- Seriously?
- My God.
- [LAUGHS]
- Oh, my.
Will you send me updates
when you hear?
- Well now, why don't you stay?
- No, I can't.
Tell you what
I could do help with.
A couple of the dikes
have come down
on the outrun there,
and I could use some help
building them back up again.
No, I've really been here
for long enough.
- London is calling me.
- All right.
I got to go back.
[INHALES]
So, because
you're gonna be rolling in it,
do you think maybe
you could lend me a few quids
just to tide me over
for when I go back?
- I just can't.
- Right. That's okay.
Have you asked your mum?
Erm, she offered to put me
into her prayers.
[LAUGHS]
ANNOUNCER: You will see
passenger emergency
instruction notices
in various parts of the vessel
and in the passenger cabins.
Please study these carefully...
Located in
the following positions,
in the restaurant...
[LAUGHTER]
[BREATHING HEAVILY]
[DISTORTED RUMBLING]
[MUFFLED CHATTER AND LAUGHTER]
[RUMBLING FADES OUT]
RONA: The urge to drink
can come out of nowhere.
[DOORBELL DINGS]
You think you're doing well.
But suddenly you want
nothing more than a drink.
When people drink,
alcohol,
or more specifically ethanol,
is absorbed
into the stomach lining
and enters the blood stream.
In the brain,
alcohol confuses messages
between neurotransmitters
and acts as both
an intoxicant and a depressant
or a relaxant.
Hiya.
DAYNIN: Hey.
- You all right?
- RONA: Yeah.
DAYNIN: That's good.
RONA: Just going to the loo.
[TOILET FLUSHING]
[SIGHS]
RONA: For those of us
susceptible to addiction,
alcohol quickly becomes
the default way
of alleviating anxiety
and dealing with
stressful situations.
Through repeated use
of the drug,
our neural pathways
are scored so deeply
they'll never be repaired.
- [INDISTINCT CHATTER ON TV]
- [LAUGHING]
[ENGINE DRONING]
- You good?
- Yeah, yeah.
- MAN: Hi, Elena.
- Hello.
It's good see you back.
Elena, this is Rona.
Rona, Elena.
ELENA: Nice to meet you.
Rona has a training day with us.
Elena quite often works for us
at the RSPB on the island.
Manages our cottage here
on Papay.
Yes.
So you gonna take us
to the holm?
Yeah, that's right.
The tides look perfect
for going there just now.
Boat's ready in the water.
The first time
that you visited Orkney?
Oh, I'm from West Mainland.
ELENA: Ah! Very nice.
MAN: We can just maybe,
like, spend
about an hour and a half there,
if that's okay with you?
WOMAN: Great.
MAN: We'll get you
back to Papay.
WOMAN: Oh, Papay really
is my favorite island.
Don't you want to stay
for a cuppa
or a coffee at Rose Cottage?
[SEAGULLS SQUAWKING]
[BOAT ENGINE WHIRRING]
MAN: So that's a grey seal,
on the rocks.
MAN 2: Yeah.
MAN: The grey seal pups,
they're all fluffy and white.
They're really nice.
And they can't swim right away.
But the common seals,
they can swim almost right away.
They can just get into the water
the same day.
[CHUCKLES SOFTLY]
People really like them.
And folk here,
what they really like
is the sound they make.
Woo!
MAN 2: Woo!
Yeah, nice one. Can you do it?
Woo!
MAN: [CHUCKLES]
A bit like a wolf.
Quite eerie,
especially if it's at night.
- [RONA GIGGLES]
- [WOMAN CHUCKLES]
RONA: Hi.
[QUIET TRANQUIL MUSIC PLAYING]
Homo sapiens have about 79%
of the same DNA as seals.
50% as plants,
a banana, a cucumber
or seaweed.
60% as jellyfish.
Jellyfish are only capable
of upwards independent movements
so they're moved horizontally
by currents and tides.
YOUNG RONA: Wait!
RONA: The day I was born,
my father became unwell.
One of the bipolar episodes
he'd had periodically
since he was a teenager.
- RONA'S MOM: Wee!
- [GIGGLING]
[SPEAKING INDISTINCTLY]
[HELICOPTER WHIRRING]
RONA: If you go mad in Orkney...
they just fly you out.
[WHIRRING]
WOMAN: So, what you've got
in front of you here
is what I would say
is a really well-mowed field.
Okay? And so what he's done
is he's gone from the inside
and he's mowed all the way out.
So that any corncrakes
that might have been
on his land in the field,
they can come all the way
into the long grass.
RONA: Mm-hmm.
WOMAN: Okay,
so when it comes to the survey,
you'll have one of these
in front of you,
- and it's like a grid system.
- Mm-hmm.
WOMAN: So you start here
from 12:00 to 3:00 a.m.
And then you go
every 200 to 500 meters...
- and then you stop.
- [ENGINE STOPS]
You wind down your window,
set a timer on your phone
for two minutes,
and you listen.
For what?
For the sound of a corncrake.
Have you heard a corncrake?
- No.
- Right. Well...
How would you describe it?
I'd say it's quite like, erm...
[HISSES]
...maybe like a cat hissing
or something.
I would say more like a cranking
chair, more something like...
[MIMICS CREAK-LIKE CALL]
- Right.
- That's good, that's good.
Get it up on YouTube for her.
- [CORNCRAKE CALLING]
- Uh-huh.
[ENGINE STARTS]
[HOUSE MUSIC PLAYING
ON CAR STEREO]
[PHONE RINGS]
[INTENSE ELECTRONIC MUSIC
PLAYING ON CAR STEREO]
[MUSIC STOPS]
DOCTOR: So, can you tell me
why you're here, Rona?
Yeah. I'm here for a referral,
for rehab.
Erm, residential.
I just want you to lock me up.
Okay. Well, there can be
quite a rate sometimes
for residential places.
But there are
some other options.
[URINATING]
COUNSELOR: This program
is a zero-tolerance
abstinence-based program.
Which means that if you
don't turn up, for any reason,
you are off the program.
It means if you relapse,
What is said in this group,
stays within
the walls of this group.
No phones.
I would ask that you only
check them at your break times.
Also, all fag
and bathroom breaks
will be accompanied
by a counselor.
Statistically, only 10%
of you will make this.
I know that sounds tough.
But it is a tough journey
that you have started.
[INDISTINCT CHATTER]
[WOMEN CHEERING AND YELLING]
Rona, come on.
No, Mum, I'm okay, thanks.
RONA'S MOM: Come on, Rona,
it's lovely.
I'm fine.
RONA'S DAD: How's Mum?
You could always just call her
and ask her yourself.
- [ROLLS DICE]
- [FOLK MUSIC PLAYING FAINTLY]
How's the job?
Erm...
Well, I haven't heard
a corncrake yet.
So not that great.
No, I can't do that.
I did find out that
there's a large population
of corncakes in Eastern Europe.
By the way, it's not ambergris.
I got the results back.
Oh.
- What is it then?
- Paraffin wax or something.
Probably.
Hmm.
Thanks for staying longer.
Hey, Dad.
I made another flower picture.
- Dad, Dad, Dad, Dad, Dad.
- [GROANS SOFTLY]
Dad, Dad, Dad, Dad, Dad.
[MELANCHOLY MUSIC PLAYING]
RONA: The past follows us.
Energy never expires.
[WAVES CRASHING]
The energy of waves
carried across the ocean
changes into noise
and heat and vibrations
that are absorbed into the land
and passed through
the generations.
Waves break when the wave height
is more than one seventh
of the wave length.
Although they collapse
in different manners,
there is only so much height
any wave can sustain
before it comes crashing down.
[DEEP HOUSE MUSIC
PLAYING ON CAR STEREO]
[MUSIC STOPS]
[INSECTS CHIRPING]
[DISTANT HOWLING]
[FAINT EERIE MUSIC PLAYING]
[SOFT, HOLLOW RUMBLING]
[MUFFLED ELECTRONIC MUSIC
FADING IN]
[MUSIC FADES]
[SERENE MUSIC PLAYING]
[DEEP HOUSE MUSIC PLAYING]
RONA: I'm so proud of you!
- Really?
- Yeah.
- Yeah, you're doing so well.
[CHEERING]
MAN: Go on, go on, go on!
Grab a shot!
- DAYNIN: Cheers, guys!
- Okay.
Make a speech!
- Don't make me make a speech.
- Come on!
- Speech! Speech!
Okay, you think
it's about me, yeah?
But I wouldn't have been able
to do it without all of you lot.
RONA: He's so humble.
- Cheers.
- Go on, go on, go on!
- [DAYNIN GROANS]
- Yes, yes, yes, yeah!
Would you want to marry me?
- [DAYNIN AND GLORIA LAUGH]
- Do I want to marry you?
Do you think
you'd want to marry me?
- Oh.
- One day, maybe.
- Maybe?
- Maybe...
One, two, three, four.
Hey! Hey, hey...
- [THUD]
- [RONA CHUCKLING]
GLORIA: For fuck's sake.
- Babe.
- RONA: Ow.
You okay?
You all right, love?
- All right, honey?
- GLORIA: Rona, babe?
RONA: Where's my compass?
GLORIA: Oh...
DAYNIN: Did you definitely
bring it out with you?
GLORIA: Did you just have it on
whilst you were dancing?
- No, don't worry, don't worry...
- It's okay. We'll find it.
- [CRYING] My compass.
- Maybe it just came off.
Have you seen...
She misses the...
- It's like this necklace thing.
- Not a necklace, it's a compass.
- GLORIA: Sorry, her compass.
- Sorry, but I didn't take it.
I don't know where it's gone.
- My dad gave me that compass.
- [LAUGHTER]
- [GLASS CLATTERS]
- Okay, okay, okay...
RONA: What are you laughing at?
- What are you laughing at?
- No one's laughing.
You think you're great
because you earn
more money than I do,
is that it?
You're not laughing now,
are you?
- Would you keep it...
- No one's laughing at you.
- Rona! Get a grip!
- [GLASS CLATTERS]
Fuck! Fuck!
What the fuck was that?
[RONA MOANS DROWSILY]
GLORIA: Okay. Okay, babe,
we need to go outside.
Rona?
DAYNIN: Rona, listen to me.
Just breathe.
Just breathe, it's okay.
You're okay.
You're okay. Just deep breaths.
You're fine, okay?
Just breathe.
- [THUD]
- Please don't.
- Rona, you're hurting yourself.
- [EXHALES]
Has she taken something?
GLORIA: No, I've not
given her anything.
Get off.
- DAYNIN: Just listen to me.
- Get off.
Double vodka.
DAYNIN: You can't order
another drink.
- We're goin'-- Oi!
- RONA: Chill out.
Go upstairs, please.
I'm too tired for this!
We're going home, all right?
No! You can't have that. Rona!
- [CRIES]
- For fuck's sake, Rona!
Be careful, hey!
[RONA BAWLING]
- Can you just listen?
- Get off!
No, no! Would you just
listen to me? I'm begging you.
- RONA: No!
- Get away from me!
Where are you going?
You're not going anywhere!
Listen to me!
You have a problem!
No, you're trying to control me.
I'm not trying
to fucking control you.
This has nothing to do with me.
- This is about you.
- [SOBBING] I hate you.
[MELANCHOLY MUSIC PLAYING]
[EXHALES]
RONA: Morning.
[GASPS]
[SIGHS SOFTLY]
What did I do last night?
You don't remember?
Daynin, I'm sorry.
[SIGHS]
Daynin, I'm so sorry,
whatever I did.
I'm not drinking anymore.
I'm sorry.
And I'm so tired
of hearing you say that.
I can't hear you say that again.
What do you mean?
I don't even
recognize you anymore.
I wish you were
a completely different person.
- Don't say that.
- I can't do this.
What do you mean
you can't do this?
I just can't do this.
Did I do that to you?
I'll never do that again. Right?
Whatever I did,
I'll never do it again.
I'm never going to drink again.
I promise you. Right?
'Cause I don't want to lose you.
I don't want to lose you.
Please don't go.
I love you.
GROUP: God,
grant me the serenity
to accept the things
that I cannot change,
the courage to change
the things that I can,
and the wisdom
to know the difference.
Thank you, Steven.
Rona, would you be happy
to share with the group today?
Perhaps some of the feelings
that you experience
when you think about drinking.
RONA: Mm-hmm.
Erm...
[INHALES]
I miss it.
I miss how good it made me feel.
[SOFT SQUELCHING]
I fell in the canal.
And I broke the bike.
But I'm gonna sort it out.
[SIGHS]
Are you gonna not say anything?
What do you want me
to say, Rona?
You're always judging me.
You're being so hard on me.
I made a mistake.
I'm sick of it.
I'm honestly... I'm sick of you.
I feel like you want me
to become one of those women
that just caters to you
and then,
with a big smile on my face
and like...
That's not the way I am.
That's not the way I'm ever
gonna be. I'm not like that.
And you know that.
I don't know why
you're expecting that from me.
You're trying to tame me.
And you're trying to control me.
[INHALES DEEPLY]
Thank you for your honesty.
MAN: Well, Rona, um...
Just want to share this...
I don't know, with you.
Basically, I... [CLEARS THROAT]
My ex-girlfriend found my stash
and threw it down the toilet.
So I thought I'd leave her
a little gift in the bed.
Which was, I just basically shat
in the bed.
- Left her a little prezzie.
- Wow.
[GROUP LAUGHS]
MAN: It's like...
MAN 2: Oh, yeah. I got one.
I got in at about
3 o'clock in the morning.
Snuck up to bed,
got into bed. Right?
Then about four or five o'clock,
I get a whack.
She has booted me, right?
Kicked me straight up
the arse, basically.
Pulled the covers up.
And I've pissed
from her neck down,
right down all through
her jarmies, everything.
[GROUP LAUGHS]
Talking of peeing, in my days...
[LAUGHS] Here we go.
- Hello.
- MAN: Hi, hi.
- How you doing?
- I'm getting on. Yeah.
- Nice to meet you.
Erm, yeah, I'm with the RSPB,
I was just wondering if I could
have a couple of minutes
- of your time.
- Yeah.
We're trying to figure out
how many corncrakes
are still on all of the islands
throughout Orkney.
And how we can actually protect
the corncrakes
- 'cause they're on the red list.
- Mm-hmm.
You want to come
in for a cup of tea?
Yeah, I will in a minute.
I'll tell you this
really, really quickly.
Basically, what we're trying
to get farmers like yourself
to do is to change
their mowing pattern.
Did your father sell the farm?
- He sold the house.
- Ah, right. Yeah.
He's still on the farm...
So where the heck
does he bide then?
- [LAUGHS] He's in a caravan.
- Oh, Lord.
Yeah.
It's enough for him, really.
It's got all his records
and stuff.
WOMAN: Good, good.
...working my way through
the whole island and...
every inhabited islands
in Orkney.
- [LAUGHS] Indeed. That's good.
- Yeah.
To see how many people
we can get on board, so...
I don't know if you'd be up
for doing something like that.
- Absolutely okay.
- Yeah.
- Yeah? Oh, really?
- Yeah. Yeah.
Okay. Great.
- Have you heard one?
- No.
- Have you not? [LAUGHS]
- Haven't heard one.
- Have you?
- You will do sometime.
I've not for a long time,
which is a bit disappointing,
'cause they used to be
quite common, but...
Yeah.
- ...things change.
- Yeah.
Because people rarely
saw the corncrake fly,
it used to be thought they'd
go underground in the winter,
transform into other species,
or even ride on other
birds' backs to migrate.
We now know that they do migrate
all the way to Central Africa.
And GPS trackers
have placed them
in Congo in the winter.
But it's
a very dangerous journey.
Only 30% make it.
[KEYS THUD]
Hi.
Daynin.
[RUNNING UP STAIRS]
[PANTING] Fuck.
[CLATTERING]
- [MELANCHOLY MUSIC PLAYING]
- [LOW RUMBLING]
[CHUGGING]
[BIRD SQUAWKING]
[SNIFFS]
That's it then, corncrakes.
MAN: So, is this
your first meeting or...
No. Good, okay.
Well, why don't we start
with the preamble as usual.
Hello. I'm James.
I'm an alcoholic.
- Hi, James.
- Hello, James.
JAMES: So, we'll do
the preamble.
Alcoholics Anonymous
is a fellowship of men and women
who share their experience,
strength and hope
with each other that they may
solve their common problem
and help others
to recover from alcoholism.
The only requirement
for membership
is a desire to stop drinking.
There are no dues or fees
for AA membership.
Our primary purpose
is to stay sober
and help other alcoholics
to achieve sobriety.
ALL: God, grant me the serenity
to accept the things
I cannot change,
the courage to change
the things that I can,
and the wisdom
to know the difference.
Amen.
Meg?
Dad.
I can't find Meg anywhere.
[WATER RUNS]
I'm just gonna leave some water
for her and some food.
But you've got to remember
to do that, okay? [SIGHS]
And I'll ask Mum
to get someone in
to just help you with the farm.
Just until you feel better.
You warm enough?
I'm scared.
I don't know
if I can do it, Dad.
[SNIFFING]
WOMAN: I wish you
a very happy future.
You deserve it.
WOMAN 2: Rona,
it's been a fantastic journey
being with you here.
I wish we had met elsewhere.
But I think
we've come a very long way.
And congratulation.
MAN: Well done, Rona.
All the best to you.
RONA: Er...
Thanks for making me strong.
I hope I don't let you down.
[CHUCKLES LIGHTLY]
Mum, are you there?
Er...
I finished, I did it, 90 days.
Yeah.
[BREATH TREMBLING]
Thanks, Mum. Erm...
Can I come up home
for a few days?
[SNIFFS]
[DISTORTED RUMBLING]
[BREATHING HEAVILY]
[RUMBLING FADES]
- [CLEARS THROAT]
- [LINE RINGING]
DAYNIN ON PHONE: Hey,
you've reached Daynin.
Leave a message
and I'll get back to you.
- [LINE BEEPS]
- Daynin.
It's me.
Don't know
if you'll get this message.
I miss you.
I miss talking to you.
I know why you left me.
I get it.
I get it. [CLEARS THROAT]
[SNIFFLING]
[BREATHES DEEPLY]
[CRYING SOFTLY]
[STOPS CRYING]
[MELANCHOLY MUSIC PLAYING]
- Cheers.
- Cheers again.
Cheers. Cheers. Cheers.
- [MUFFLED CHATTER]
- [SEAGULLS CALLING]
This is a great moment.
We're all together.
[OBJECTS CLATTERING]
[DRUNKENLY]
Where are the apples?
The apples...
Oh, shit. [CHUCKLES]
I was just getting an apple.
[GROANS SOFTLY]
He's not real, you know.
They have you brainwashed.
Come to bed, Rona.
That's why Dad left you,
you know.
Because you chose them over us.
I can't believe that
you still believe... [LAUGHS]
You're so stupid.
There's another one.
Lies.
[BREATHING HEAVILY]
[SNIFFLING]
All that praying didn't help,
did it, Mum?
It didn't help me. [SOBBING]
- Go on, lie down.
- Didn't help me.
Come on.
[TEARFULLY] I'm sorry, Mum.
[SOBS]
[DROWSILY] I'm sorry, Mummy.
[SWITCH CLICKS]
[ENGINE DRONING]
ELENA: Washing machine, cooker,
pots and pans, and the stove.
Watch the handle
for it can get hot.
Erm, there's firewood there
and there's more in the shed.
- Okay.
- But when it gets really cold,
you might want to order
a bag of coal from the shop.
It's pretty rough
in the winter time.
Er, no fancy going somewhere
warmer like the Canary Islands
- or somewhere like that?
- Yeah,
it's cheaper to come to Papay.
Well, that is very true.
Er, this is your bedroom,
living room.
It still smells a bit fusty.
Erm...
But there's the bed.
It's quite cozy.
And, well,
we meet on a Wednesday
in the hall, if you fancy
a cup of tea and a blether.
We're just 60 people
but there's plenty going on.
If you're wanting
a bit of company?
- Yeah, I might do, yeah. Maybe.
- Okay.
I'll away. I've got stuff to do,
and I'll see you soon.
- Have you got the keys?
- Oh. Sorry.
- It's all right.
- Not that we need them.
- Thanks, Elena.
- Not in Papay.
You take care, Rona.
- Bye.
- Cheerio.
[DOOR CLOSES]
[CAR ENGINE STARTS]
[SIGHS]
[ENGINE ACCELERATING]
[MELANCHOLY MUSIC PLAYING]
RONA: Britain is an island
off Europe.
Orkney is an island
off Scotland.
Westray is an island off Orkney.
Papay is an island off Westray.
According to Orcadian folklore,
the island Hether Blether
only appears in the fog.
It was said that once a girl
was kidnapped by a finman
and taken
to the mystical island,
and never could return.
Hi, Mum, it's me.
Erm, sorry I didn't
get to see you
before I went to the airport.
I just wanted to let you know
that I got to Papay safely.
[SIGHS] Erm...
I don't know yet how long
I'm going to stay.
A couple of months, I think.
The signal is not great here,
but it would be good
to hear from you.
[WIND HOWLING]
[GRUNTS SOFTLY]
[MELANCHOLY MUSIC PLAYING]
[RAIN PATTERING]
Whoo-hoo!
Yes!
And I see mornings
with high heating bills.
- [LAUGHING]
- And with every crumb
that fell from your lips
onto fresh bed linen sheets...
[RETCHING AND VOMITING]
[BOTH LAUGHING]
- Why don't you come outside?
- GLORIA: Let's have a--
- Have a bit of fresh air?
- Okay, okay! You get off of me!
[DOORBELL RINGING]
Open the door, Daynin!
Answer me! [GROANS]
[MAN PANTING]
Why are you doing this to me?
Piece of shit,
I hope you fucking die in hell.
So, how does London
compare to Papay?
RONA: Er, well...
there's a bit more going on.
I guess.
ELENA: I'll bet.
RONA: Have you ever been
down south?
Sometimes, not very often.
Not very often. [CHUCKLES]
We hardly get away
and my husband's going,
"Oh, I can't see
the sea and the trees.
And you can't see anything.
When are we going home?"
MAN: Spot on.
SHOPKEEPER: Thank you very much.
All the very best.
MAN: See you soon.
SHOPKEEPER: See you again.
Over there.
Last few casks of these...
MAN 2: Well, indeed, fine.
SHOPKEEPER: Thank you very much.
- Thank you.
- Good seeing the pair of you.
- All the very best.
- Yes, I'll see you around, sir.
Cheers, bye.
Cheers, all the best.
MAN 2: And you.
- SHOPKEEPER: Hi, hi.
- Hi, hi.
- How's it going?
- Good.
SHOPKEEPER: Lovely.
ELENA: I should introduce you
to my brother, Calum.
- Oh, hello. Rona.
- Hi. How are you doing?
Hi, Rona.
Good to see you.
Rose Cottage?
Mm. Aye.
CALUM: Is it, uh,
bird work you're doing?
- Calum, stop.
- Ugh.
He's so nosy,
he's like an old wife.
CALUM: Well, erm, I was
the warden of the nature reserve
up there, back in the '80s.
- Right.
- Before we had Rose Cottage.
I stayed at Gowrie
just across the way.
It was very basic.
Rose Cottage is a palace.
Gowrie was a hovel.
But it was my hovel.
I loved it very much.
Erm, could I get some tobacco
as well, please?
CALUM: Sure. Yeah, yeah.
Is that it? Got everything?
- Yeah, yeah.
- Okay.
[SNIFFS, CLEARS THROAT]
[SERENE MUSIC PLAYING
ON SPEAKERS]
[EXHALES DEEPLY]
[BREATHING DEEPLY]
[TURNS MUSIC OFF]
[BREATHES DEEPLY]
[SEAGULLS CALLING IN DISTANCE]
[WAVES RUMBLING]
[THUNDER RUMBLING]
[WIND WHISTLING]
[GRUNTING]
[PANTING]
RONA: The original
Beaufort scale
didn't give wind speed
in miles per hour,
but rather in terms
of its effects on sailing ships.
From "just sufficient
to give steerage"
to "that which no canvas sails
could withstand."
[WIND BLOWING]
The wind is our most defining
weather in Orkney.
Even in summer,
there's usually a breeze.
Beaufort force three or four
on average.
In Winter, gales are common.
- [INTENSE QUARELLING]
- [WINDOW SMASHING]
- [GLASS SMASHES]
- [RONA'S MOM SCREAMS]
RONA'S DAD: Come in! Come in!
I am one with the wind.
RONA'S MOM:
You're upsetting her!
- [WIND WHISTLING]
- RONA'S DAD: Oh. Oh!
RONA'S MOM: Andrew... [SOBS]
ANDREW: Beautiful that is.
Beautiful, listen to it.
Breathe it in! Breathe it in!
- RONA'S MOM: Lord, God...
- We are one with the wind.
RONA'S MOM: Oh, God,
please help him!
[MELANCHOLY MUSIC PLAYING]
ANDREW: You don't understand.
[QUARELLING CONTINUES
INDISTINCTLY]
[MELANCHOLY MUSIC CONTINUES]
- [WIND BLOWING]
- [MUSIC FADES OUT]
[LAUGHING] King of the castle.
[CHUCKLES]
My subjects.
Welcome to my house.
- [SHEEP BLEATING]
- [LAUGHTER]
Rona, get in here!
I'm going to watch.
All right, if you're
not going to come in...
[SOFT FOLK MUSIC PLAYING]
- [WOMAN SPEAKS INDISTINCTLY]
- Aaah! [LAUGHS]
You having fun?
- Nah, I'm having an awful time.
- Looks like it.
Really reminds me of home,
you know?
MAN: I forget
you're a farm girl.
- Aahil! Really?
- What?
- You really need to do that?
- What's the big deal?
What do you mean,
"It's not a big deal"?
Pick it up. It's not a bin.
- All right, all right.
- That's what the big deal is.
- [RONA CHUCKLES]
- For fuck's sake.
You know, he's terrified of you.
He's not terrified
of me, just...
- Yes.
- He knows I'm right.
You know...
I'd never let my boys get away
with any of that shit.
What do you mean, your boys?
- [COUGHS]
- You have kids?
Yes, I have two boys.
- Really?
- Yeah.
It's why I get up
every morning, it's...
you know, for them.
[SNIFFS, MUTTERS]
So, what age are they?
- Seventeen.
- Seventeen?
Yeah, 14.
I've not seen them in ten years,
though, so...
Better that way, who wants a...
You know, who wants
a crackhead for a dad?
Once I'm clean and...
Then I'll bring them here.
We're nearly done here.
What are you going to do
after all of this?
Don't know.
Nothing.
WOMAN: We can see if we can get
a horse ride set up.
I fucked it up.
- I did.
- Hang on, hang on.
- [IMITATES SAD VIOLIN NOTES]
- Shut up. You asked.
- [LAUGHS]
- You asked.
Well... Come on, listen.
See, I don't mean to...
Look at this brigade.
If they can make it,
you can make it. [CHUCKLES]
RONA: I don't know about that.
MAN: You'll be fine.
I can't be happy sober.
[ELECTRONIC MUSIC PLAYING
ON HEADPHONES]
[SEAGULLS SQUAWKING]
Hi, Rona.
- Hiya.
- Hiya, how are you doing?
- Good, how are you?
- Not bad at all.
What a lovely day,
isn't it a cracker?
You getting in
among the seaweeds?
- [CHUCKLES] Aye.
- You've come to the right place.
- It's a seaweed supermarket.
- [CHUCKLES SOFTLY]
Are you doing well?
- Lovely, lovely.
- Yeah.
Well, I've just been doing
a spot of beachcombing.
What do you make of this?
- The city of New York.
- [CHUCKLES]
Very nice.
Well...
Well, I'll let you get on.
And, er,
if there's anything you need,
just give us a shout, okay?
- Okay? Righto.
- Yeah, I will. Yeah.
- All the best. Cheerio for now.
- See you. Bye.
[ELECTRONIC MUSIC CONTINUES]
[SOOTHING MUSIC PLAYING]
[SKYPE RINGING]
- Ro, Ro, there you are! Listen!
- Hi.
- [MUSIC PLAYS ON SPEAKERS]
- This storm came through
and I've had to patch up
another window.
Oh, no!
I've almost run out
of gaffer tape.
Right, and you've got to get
that fixed then, don't you?
But listen, the real reason
I want to talk to you is
I've been in touch with the bank
and I've arranged a loan.
- But for what, Dad?
- I've not arranged it yet,
but I will do.
Can you turn the music down?
I can't hear you very well.
Dad, can you turn
the music down?
I was in touch
with a fella from south
who's an intern on one of
these offshore wind farms and...
and the other thing is there's
a... Hey, you'll love this.
I was talking
to the geothermal physicist
about the caves
under the ground there
- because I own them.
- Dad, have you been sleeping?
And the thing
about geothermal thing
is it's all about the storage.
Okay. Dad? You need to sleep.
And there's fluctuations
in the wind speed.
You're not sleeping, are you?
Because you're getting high.
- Ro! Ro! Ro!
- Yes, I'm listening to you.
- I've no time for this.
- You need to calm down, okay?
This is the avant garde,
I am on the forefront
of the ecological revolution.
This is wonderful work!
Will you please take
some sleeping pills
and just go to sleep
for a few hours?
[HOUSE MUSIC PLAYING]
[MUSIC STOPS]
[SEAGULL SQUAWKING]
Ah.
[BREATHING HEAVILY]
Oh, God.
[KEYBOARD CLACKING]
[WAVES RUMBLING]
[PHONE VIBRATING]
[CLEARS THROAT]
Hello?
Er, yeah, I'd love
to talk to him. Thank you.
- ANDREW: Ro.
- Hiya, Dad.
- Rona? Hello?
- Yeah, are you okay?
- Hello? Rona?
- Hiya.
- It's Dad.
- Yeah.
Listen, I have
a really important...
[FUMBLING] Did you...
Would you mind giving me some...
[SIGHS]
- Well. Sorry, I...
- Dad, are you okay?
Are you all right in there?
Listen, I have to talk
very quietly, I'm surrounded.
- Okay.
- I'm being held against my will
in an institution.
And I need your help
to facilitate my release.
Do you think you can do that?
No, Dad, because you have to
stay there until you get better.
God! God!
You put me in here
in the first place
and you won't give yourself
the opportunity
to redeem yourself
by getting me out.
- Dad, I didn't put you anywhere.
- Listen...
You goddamn, you know
bloody well what you did.
- What did I do?
- You called the cops.
Dad, I didn't call the cops.
Not at all.
You called the cops.
They came and they took me away.
I know, Dad,
but I think it's because
- everyone was worried about you.
- No!
I think somebody else called.
[GRUNTS] You break my heart.
You break my heart.
[BREATH TREMBLING]
You are a deceitful woman.
You are a...
[BREATHING DEEPLY]
[MELANCHOLY MUSIC PLAYING]
Okay.
Don't disappoint me any more
than you already have, Rona.
I'm gonna go. I'll check in
with you later, okay?
Rona! Now, you pull your...
- RONA: Fuck!
- [OBJECTS CLATTER]
[MELANCHOLY MUSIC CONTINUES]
[BIRDS CHIRPING]
[BREATHING HEAVILY]
[RUMBLING]
[PANTING]
[GROANING SOFTLY]
MAN: Hey, you need a ride?
[WHIMPERS]
[SOBS]
MAN: I can give you a lift,
if you like.
RONA: To Daynin's house.
MAN: Good.
I'll take you there. Jump in.
Thank you.
[GROGGILY] Hi. Hiya.
Well, I bumped into someone
who's giving me a lift to yours,
because he knows where you live.
[ENGINE SWITCHES OFF]
[BOTH GRUNTING]
- MAN: Don't you want it?
- [RONA SCREAMING]
You bitch!
RONA: Help me!
Help!
[RONA SCREAMS]
MAN: Shit!
RONA: No, help me!
MAN: Come back here. Wait!
RONA: Help!
- [SIREN WAILING IN DISTANCE]
- [CAR STARTING AND ACCELERATING]
[CAMERA CLICKING]
[SOFT EMOTIONAL MUSIC PLAYING]
Hi.
DAYNIN: Hey.
[DAYNIN INHALES DEEPLY]
[RONA SIGHS]
So, how have you been?
I'm good.
How's your job?
[SIGHS HEAVILY]
- I mean, I got that promotion.
- Oh, wow.
Big boss man now.
- Got an assistant.
- Ah.
- Office?
- Tiny one.
[RONA CHUCKLES]
Are you seeing anyone
or anything?
Yeah.
Right.
She is nice.
Kind, you know.
- It's different.
- Mm-hmm.
It's boring, I bet.
[CHUCKLES SOFTLY]
I'm glad you're happy.
I like your hair.
Oh, yeah?
Yeah.
It's nice.
MAN: Fuck you!
[LAUGHTER AND CHATTER]
You wanna go for a drink?
[SIGHS]
[INHALES DEEPLY]
[INDUSTRIAL MUSIC PLAYING
ON HEADPHONES]
- [MUSIC FADES]
- [WAVES CRASHING]
[SEAGULLS CALLING]
[WAVES RUMBLING]
RONA: There's a berg.
Lads, there's a berg,
there's a berg!
- To the starboard.
- [WHOOSHING]
Woo! Steady as she goes, lads.
Steady as she goes!
We got a berg
to the starboard, lads!
You gotta hustle up, hustle up.
Go on.
Okay.
[GRUNTS]
- [WIND BLOWING]
- Crow's nest!
Can you hear me?
Is it all clear up north?
Yep, we're heading north.
[INDISTINCT CHATTER]
[BAND PLAYING LIVELY FOLK MUSIC]
[CROWD CHEERING]
[MUSIC STOPS]
[CROWD LAUGHING]
- [BAND RESUMES PLAYING]
- Come on, come on!
[CROWD CLAPPING RHYTHMICALLY]
- [MUSIC ENDS]
- [CROWD CHEERING]
Well done. You did really well.
- [INDISTINCT CHATTER]
- [SIGHS]
[MUSIC PLAYING INSIDE]
- Hi, Rona.
- Hiya, you all right?
- Aye, not bad. How is yourself?
- Yeah, I'm good.
Just had to get a bit of air,
it was getting
really hot in there.
Aye, all right, not half.
There's a lot going on.
- Aye.
So how long you been sober?
Sixty-three days.
Wow.
That's the steepest bit
you've done.
So, what about you?
Oh, boy. Erm...
Twelve years.
Four months.
And...
twenty-nine days.
Damn.
How is that?
Well, it's okay.
Started off one day at a time.
Twelve years
and four months later,
it's still one day at a time.
Because that's the only way.
And it works.
And you're doing it.
So it gets easier, does it?
Oh, yes. Yes, it does.
- You have my word on that.
- Mm.
But... [SIGHS]
it never gets easy.
It just gets less hard.
[WIND HOWLING]
[WIND GUSTING]
[LIGHTER CLICKS]
[PENSIVE MUSIC PLAYING]
[TYPING]
RONA: The marine traffic
and flight radar websites
show in real-time
the paths of all vessels at sea
and all commercial aircraft
in the sky.
A light that moves
above the cottage
is a Lufthansa flight
from Los Angeles to Frankfurt.
[NOTIFICATION CHIMES]
I monitor the path of
the International Space Station.
And find out
when it's passing over.
[NOTIFICATION CHIMING
INTERMITTENTLY]
Tonight it flies over Orkney.
- Merry Christmas.
- ELENA: Hi, Rona.
Not got good news.
There's no flights
coming in today.
What?
There's a technical fault
with the plane.
And there's no flights
coming in at all.
What about tomorrow?
No, they're waiting on parts
and engineers and...
- [SIGHS]
- And I'm afraid
the boats are away
into the town for Christmas.
RADIO ANNOUNCER:
A fresh kinda day
with strong
easterly winds and rain.
Winds are likely
to get up to near gale force
just before midday,
but they will ease off
for the afternoon.
Temperatures will be struggling
to get into double figures.
Maybe nine degrees Celsius
at a push. That's just...
[BREATHING HEAVILY]
[SHIVERING]
[EXHALES HEAVILY]
[BREATH SHUDDERING]
[SERENE MUSIC FADING IN]
Woo!
[RONA PANTING]
[GASPING]
Woo!
[SEAL HOWLS]
[RONA CHUCKLES]
[SCREAMS IN EXCITEMENT]
[SERENE MUSIC CONTINUES]
[SEAL HOWLS]
[RONA CHUCKLES]
[PANTING AND CHUCKLING]
[CONTINUES CHUCKLING]
[SIGHS]
[SEAL HOWLING]
- CALUM: Hey, Rona.
- Hi.
- How are you doing?
- Good.
You been for a swim?
- Yeah. [GIGGLES]
- Fantastic. Gosh, look at you.
[SHOWER RUNNING]
[GROANS]
[CHEERFUL MUSIC
PLAYING ON SPEAKERS]
[SINGING ALONG] For you
My heart cries out, Perfidia
For I found you
the love of my life...
MAN 1 ON TV: Move!
MAN 2 ON TV: Get it out!
- [RONA GIGGLING]
- MAN 3: It's back on me now.
It's on me.
Get the pigeon off me.
MAN 2: It's not on you.
- MAN 3: Well, it is!
- [LAUGHS]
MAN 2: I'm gonna get it
with the...
Come back here, sir...
young lad.
[DISCO MUSIC PLAYING
ON SPEAKERS]
Come on!
- [MUSIC CONTINUES]
- [PANTING]
[BEAT DROPS]
[WIND WHISTLING]
Hey.
- How is it?
- Windy.
RONA: Yeah.
Elena, this is my mum.
Oh.
Oh, it's really nice
to meet you.
Yeah, nice to meet you, too.
- You have a lovely daughter.
- Yeah, thank you.
- She's been looking after me.
- Oh!
RONA: They're just some drawings
I've done and stuff.
[CHUCKLES SOFTLY]
Do you want a cup of tea?
- Oh, yes.
- It's warmer in the kitchen.
- Shall we go there?
- Lovely, thank you.
And I made some bread.
And it's your recipe.
Oh, Rona, that looks wonderful.
- RONA: It may poison you.
- [CHUCKLES]
- So, do you like it?
- Mm.
So, how long do you think
you'll stay here for?
Erm...
Don't know,
probably till the spring.
- That long?
- Yeah.
Well, I'm thinking
about changing my PhD.
I've become really,
really fascinated with seaweed
and the whole seaweed industry.
Seaweed farming
is kind of changing the world.
It's always been around
in eastern parts of the world.
And, yeah,
we're not really exploring that
as much as we used to.
So, what I'm thinking
about doing
is studying seaweed farming.
So, I started to look into it
and there's all these
different benefits to seaweed.
There's, you know,
soil fertilizers.
If you feed it to cows,
it's a really great way,
a great natural way
to fertilize the soil.
The cattle produce less methane
when they burp
and when they fart.
And, you know,
it supplies your body
with magnesium, copper,
all these different things.
It also supplies the earth
with 60% of its oxygen.
I thought
that was the rainforest.
No. Common misconception,
but it's marine plants.
It's in our toothpaste.
It's part of our culture,
our mythology, everything.
If everyone
got on board with it,
it could change the world.
And so,
I want to be a part of it.
How is Dad?
RONA'S MOM:
He's coming home next week.
Where is he going to stay?
The caravan on the farm,
of course.
Of course.
I mean, we're not going to
get him to live anywhere else,
- are we?
- Absolutely not.
I should go back then.
At least I can cook for him,
I can get him stuff in.
RONA'S MOM: Rona, please,
don't worry so much.
- RONA: But I do worry.
- No.
He's had to go through this
over and over again.
You know,
you have to look after yourself.
That's what I had to do,
you know. [INHALES DEEPLY]
Was it really hard for you?
Just having me, having the farm,
he just wasn't... there.
Mm, it was.
It was.
At times it was very difficult.
He'd be away for months.
And then even when
he wasn't away, I was...
very lonely, sometimes.
- Mm.
- Yeah.
Then I found God, or rather...
God found me.
Mm.
[SERENE MUSIC PLAYING]
RONA: All things come
from the ocean.
And the ocean takes them back.
And eventually, one day,
they might come back again
to the land.
After a gale is when
the best things are found.
Parts of the Udal Law
from old Norse times
still apply in Orkney.
And if you find something
on the shore of your farmland,
and its above
the low water mark,
it's yours.
[BOAT HORN BLOWS]
[SERENE MUSIC CONTINUES]
[INDISTINCT CHATTER]
There's a festival
that's about to happen here,
it's called the Gyro Nights.
GLORIA: Oh.
So all these artists
from all over the country,
all over the world actually
are coming in.
And we've been, like,
arranging the whole thing.
And putting banners up.
- Oh, yeah?
- Mm-hmm.
- You're coming for my job.
- [LAUGHS]
So, erm, no, but really,
how are you doing?
I'm fine.
- I'm actually, yeah...
- I mean, you look great, like...
I'm probably the best I've been
in a really long time.
Promise.
[GIGGLES]
[CHUCKLES]
- [PLAYING UPBEAT FOLK MUSIC]
- [INDISTINCT CHATTER]
ALL: Gyro!
Gyro!
WOMAN: I got it. Yeah, I got it.
[LAUGHTER]
[CHEERING]
[BLOWS]
RONA: Do you want to sit down?
Yeah, please. [CHUCKLES]
- It's a bit messy.
- That's okay.
Here you go.
[MAN BLOWS]
So cold.
Do you mind
if I take my socks off?
No. That's what I'm gonna do.
MAN: Soaking wet.
Give me the socks.
Thank you.
[BLOWS]
- Ah, that's better.
- So much better.
I loved that tonight,
it was fun.
Such a nice evening.
I actually had a dream
the other night
- that all my hair was on fire.
- Okay.
- [BOTH LAUGH]
- That sounds quite scary.
Yeah. Kind of amazing, though.
My hair was just flames
running around.
So, you go back tomorrow?
Yeah, getting the ferry
in the morning.
RONA: Hmm.
Hmm.
[FIRE CRACKLING]
[REFLECTIVE MUSIC PLAYING]
RONA: In grandiose moments,
high on fresh air
and freedom on the hill,
I study my personal geology.
My body is a continent.
I grind my teeth in my sleep
like tectonic plates.
And when I blink,
the sun flickers.
My breath pushes the clouds
across the sky.
And the waves roll
in to the shore
in time with my beating heart.
The island's headlands
rise above the sea
like my limbs in the bathtub.
My freckles
are famous landmarks.
And my tears, rivers.
Lightning strikes
every time I sneeze.
And when I orgasm,
there is an earthquake.
[FLAME RUMBLING]
[REFLECTIVE MUSIC CONTINUES]
[KISSES]
[SEAGULLS CALLING]
[REFLECTIVE MUSIC CONTINUES]
[UPLIFTING MUSIC MERGING IN]
[INTENSE ELECTRONIC MUSIC
MERGING IN]
[MUSIC SOARING]
[INTENSE FUSION MUSIC PLAYING]
[MUSIC BUILDING]
[MUSIC ENDS]
[PANTING]
[WAVES CRASHING]
[BIRDS CHIRPING]
- [CORNCRAKE CALLS]
- Mm?
[RONA LAUGHS IN DISBELIEF]
[SYNTHPOP MUSIC PLAYING]
[SYNTHPOP MUSIC ENDS]
- [WAVES CRASHING GENTLY]
- [BIRDS CHIRPING]
[CORNCRAKE CALLS]